<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>True newes of a notable victorie obtayned against the Turkes, by the right honourable Lorde, Adolph Baron of Swartzburg, the 18. day of March last past, anno 1598 vvhen as he and his armie three houres before day, came before Raab, and tooke in that strong and well fenced hold and cittie / translated out of the high Dutch coppy ; printed first at Nurnbergh &amp;c. ; by W.S.R.</title>
            <author>W. S. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20595.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23065303</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23065303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26166</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10310)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1779:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>True newes of a notable victorie obtayned against the Turkes, by the right honourable Lorde, Adolph Baron of Swartzburg, the 18. day of March last past, anno 1598 vvhen as he and his armie three houres before day, came before Raab, and tooke in that strong and well fenced hold and cittie / translated out of the high Dutch coppy ; printed first at Nurnbergh &amp;c. ; by W.S.R.</title>
                  <author>W. S. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 [i.e. 12] p. : 2 ports.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I.R. for Richard Oliue, and are to be sold at his shop in Long-lane, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1598]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A2) B⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Pagination starts with 5 on third page of item.</note>
                  <note>T.p. contains portrait of Lord Adolph.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Győr (Hungary) --  History, Military.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  History --  1526-1683.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26166:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>True Newes</hi> Of a notable victorie obtayned <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Turkes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Right honourable Lorde, <hi>Adolph</hi> Baron of
<hi>Swartzburg,</hi> the 18. day of March laſt paſt, Anno 1598. VVhen as he and his Armie three houres before day, came before <hi>Raab:</hi> And tooke in that ſtrong and well fenced Hold and Cittie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the high Dutch coppy, printed first at</hi> Nurnbergh. &amp;c. By W.S.R.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>The true counterfeit of the Lord Adolph.</head>
               <figDesc>portrait of Baron Adolf zu Schwarzenberg</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by I.R. for Richard Oliue, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Long-lane, at the ſigne of the Bible.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:26166:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:26166:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>True Newes</hi> Of a notable victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie obtayned againſt the <hi>Turkes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith what deceitfull craft, and falſe practiſes, (the outragious Enemie of Chriſtendome) the Turk a fewe yéeres paſt, through the permiſſion of God, and for our ſinnes, tooke in the ſtrong and well defenced holde of <hi>Raab</hi> in Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, and with all other Fortreſſes lying on the frontiers, whereby no ſmall loſſe and damage is hetherto growne vnto all Chriſtendome: is well knowne vnto many.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch, as GOD himſelfe, had euen ſo ſmal pleaſure, in ſuch falſe practiſes, and crafty deceit of the enemie, as of our owne ſinnes, whereby wee daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke him, that he ſuffereth the enemy to raigne ouer vs, he hath with his grace turned againe to vs, and giuen his Chriſtian ſouldiours a hart and courage, that they and theyr whole company co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming before the ſaid Hold, by the power and help of GOD, haue wonderfully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and wonne the ſame. For which glorious victorie, the ſame almighty God bee prayſed and thanked for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and that hee will be ſtill aſſiſtant to his Chriſtian people, to deſtroy and defend the Enemie, for his moſt holy Names ſake, Amen.</p>
            <div type="body_of_account">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26166:3"/>
               <head>The whole circumſtances as it happened, of the getting thereof, is contayned briefely in a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written to the Emperours Maieſtie, as followeth.</head>
               <p>THE Lord <hi>Adolph</hi> of <hi>Swartzburg,</hi> beeing credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly informed, that the Turkes of <hi>Raab,</hi> were gone forth on forraging: departed out of <hi>Camorr</hi> the <hi>18.</hi> day of March,
<hi>1598.</hi> with certaine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of well appointed Souldiers on horſebacke and on foote, and with the Lord <hi>Palfy,</hi> with thoſe his Hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducks, Huſſerns, and certaine Duch men of <hi>Strigonia,</hi> and ſo ſecretly encamped in a vale or holow place, about three leagues from
<hi>Raab.</hi> From thence hes preſently ſent about midnight, a hundred choſen men on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe and on foote, before to <hi>Raab,</hi> with certaine wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, laden with Boate-bridges, Skaling-ladders, and inſtruments of fire-workes. But he himſelfe with the reſt of his Souldiers, followed ſoftly after.</p>
               <p>In which expedition, almightie God wonderfullie ſhewed his goodnes towards vs.</p>
               <p>For euen as the Chriſtian Souldiers approched nere vnto
<hi>Raab,</hi> and the Moone ſhyning ſo light and ſo cléere, that they might eaſily haue been ſéene, perceiued, and knowne of the Enemie: ſuddainly a long, thick &amp; black cloude, couered the Moone in ſuch ſort, that they coulde ſcant diſcerne one another.</p>
               <p>In which ſuddaine darkning of the Moone: there aroſe alſo a great winde, and withall, a miſt. Which winde did driue the noyſe of our Souldiers and theyr furniture backe from the Enemy, and theyr comming ſo vnlooked for, that they could not perceiue any thing at all. When the Foreward was come to <hi>Raab</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beeing perceiued as afore-ſaid), they found the draw <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26166:3"/>bridge downe, and the Portcullis drawne vp. Becauſe the Turkes of <hi>Raab,</hi> looked euery houre for certain wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of prouender to come from
<hi>Stulweiſsenburg,</hi> and feared no inuaſion at this time.</p>
               <p>Which good oportunitie our men quickly percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, paſſed ouer the bridge to the gate, faſtning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of fire workes, and kindling of the ſame, which wrought not at the very firſt, but yet at laſt with the greater force, it did teare, &amp; breake both gate, wall, and whatſoeuer els it lighted on, and made ſuch way, that they in the forward, thruſt into the Holde, making haſt to the watch, which they killed. And certaine alſo, tooke in the principall Bulwarks, and ſome fired the Ordinance at the gate.</p>
               <p>In which time, the reſt of the company were not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, but with great violence did fall in, helping their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that they that came firſt, tooke the Ordinance at the <hi>Weiſſenburgiſh</hi> gate, and diſcharged the ſame from the carriage, that the Turkes could not come to ſhoote of the ſame, againſt the reſt of our people, which were yet without.</p>
               <p>When the Turkes perceiued it: they defended them ſelues very valiantly and manfully: wherof many that were lying in their bedde, and feared no ſuch danger, came ſpeedily running out in their ſhirts, as in haſt and for feare, not making themſelues ready, defending the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtoutly, but yet all in vaine, for they were all kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>The Lorde <hi>Adolph</hi> of <hi>Swartzburg,</hi> with certaine great Ordinance, went before the Caſtle, and with ſhooting opened the ſame, wherein he found about <hi>600.</hi> Turks, which thought to haue ſaued themſelues, which were all ſlaine, with the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of
<hi>Raab.</hi> The <hi>Baſſa</hi> had in each hand a Sabel, and defended himſelfe ſo ſtoutly and manfully, that he could not be taken aliue, but was laſtly thruſt through by a <hi>Wallon,</hi> his heade ſticked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26166:4"/>a pole, and ſette ouer the Hungarian Bulwarke.</p>
               <p>There were alſo about <hi>300.</hi> crept vnderneth a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark, wherein ſtoode certaine barrels of Gunpowder. Which our men comming vnto, the Turkes would not yéeld themſelues, as alſo not looking for any fauour at our hands: they ſette the Gunpowder on fire, ſplitte the Bulwarke, ſpoiled themſelues, and about <hi>300.</hi> of our men, which were then vppon the Bulwarke. Which was a great loſſe, aſwell to our men, as to themſelues. Which if it had not happened: it was thought, wee had not loſt aboue <hi>200.</hi> of our people.</p>
               <p>But in the ſame vnlooked for ſkirmiſh (which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued fiue houres) there was ſlayne of our men, about <hi>600.</hi> And of the Turks, about <hi>1500.</hi> men. There was taken aboue <hi>300.</hi> amongſt the which was a <hi>Beglerbeg,</hi> the <hi>Baſſaes</hi> ſonne, and two of his Daughters. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, our men found about <hi>400.</hi> Chriſtians there, and releaſed them.</p>
               <p>It was alſo well furniſhed with victuals and other prouiſions, and almoſt in euery houſe, was great ſtore found.</p>
               <p>Of Ordinance, on the wals and Bulwarks: there was
<hi>120.</hi> Peeces vpon whéeles, and there lie yet in the Fort
<hi>50.</hi> Peeces, without Carriages.</p>
               <p>Our people had alſo ſo ſtopped all the gates of
<hi>Raab,</hi> that not one could come forth, to tell the other Turkes neere at hand. So that the Turkes of <hi>Stulweiſſenburg,</hi> ſent <hi>40.</hi> Waggons of victuals and munition, gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; long Péeces, ſtrongly conducted with Souldiers, to <hi>Raab.</hi> Which came thether euen as the ſkirmiſh was ended, who knowing nothing of their great loſſes and hurts: euer made haſt towards the Towne. When they came to the Bridge, thinking no otherwiſe but that they were néere their friends: our men did let them come in, one after another. But gaue them ſuch ill entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that none eſcaped aliue. Where vnto the Lord
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26166:4"/>
                  <hi>Palfi</hi> helped well: for as they ſo paſſed in good order to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Raab,</hi> he departed out of his Bulwarke with his folke, enuironing them behind, ſlaying them, that none could eſcape. For looke what could not rearh to the Towne: The ſame did the Lord <hi>Palſi,</hi> lay hold on, and ſlew.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The true counterfet of the Lord Palſi.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Likewiſe was there many of the principalleſt Turks, which were gone out of <hi>Raab,</hi> on forraging (as it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the beginning) comming home, and becauſe they knew nothing of their great loſſe, they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues more ſurer: but our men fell vpon them, and ſlew them. By whom our men alſo found, (as thee did in the Towne) great treaſure, of gold, ſiluer, precious ſtones, and apparell. And haue brought away about <hi>600.</hi> faire Turkiſh horſes.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:26166:5"/>
               <p>And ſo, and in this manner (God be therefore euer prayſed and thanked) was this worthy place gotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, which the vehement Enemy with treachery had gotten from the Chriſtians, &amp; without reaſon p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſeſſed. And eſpecially through the manfull courage of the chiefe Generall, The Lord
<hi>Adolph</hi> Baron of <hi>Swartzburg,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and brought to Chriſtendome. Where-vnto alſo the honourable Lord <hi>Palſi,</hi> with his retinue, truly helped.</p>
               <p>As the ſayd Lord <hi>Adolph,</hi> in his firſt Letter to the Emperors maieſty prayſeth him, that he in expedition of theſe affaires, behaued himſelfe valiantly, as hee alſo writeth of the other Captaines, Lieuetenants, &amp; whole company. That they in this ſeruice of importance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued themſelues according to his minde, and kept the order appoynted them. And withall declareth, that if he might be ſoone helped with Horſe-men and Foote-men: he would with Gods help, ſeeke his good fortune, in ſome other place.</p>
               <p>When theſe newes, were truly brought to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: his Maieſty thanked GOD for ſuch a glorions victory. And the people w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re with <hi>18.</hi> Trumpetters, and with Droms, called to the Church, where all the whole congregation did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing,
<hi>Wee prayſe thee ô God.</hi> After which, there followed a Sermon, which Sermon, and thankſ-giuing being finiſhed: There was at the
<hi>Lion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe 18.</hi> great Péeces of Ordinance, each thrée times ſhot of, for ioy of the obtayned victory. And through the whole Citty, was a ioyfull feaſt holden, to the prayſe and honour of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exhortation">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:26166:5"/>
               <head>A CHRISTIAN EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, whereby we are admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to giue thanks with our harts, for the obtayned victory: as alſo to true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and earneſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as God in old time, by his Prophet, denounced that
<hi>Iſraell</hi> in <hi>Aſſiria</hi> and <hi>Iury,</hi> with their Kings and Princes, wiues and children, ſhould he carried away to <hi>Babilon,</hi> the Land deſtroyed, and all by reaſon of ſinne, falſe Doctrine, and Idolatry: yet they notwithſtanding deſpiſed all warning and admonition, perſecuted the Prophets, and fauoured yet their ſinnes, till that they gaue the Lord cauſe, to thruſt them out of his ſight. Euen ſo, and in like manner, hath God our Chriſt, in the latter dayes of the world, alſo denounced vnto vs, of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, Meſech</hi> and
<hi>Thubal.</hi> which are euen the Turkes, Tarters, and ſuch like people. That they with great multitudes ſhould ouer-runne, harry, and ſpoyle Chriſtendome, and all through his wrath, by reaſon of our ſinne. For thus ſayth the Lord, in the <hi>38.</hi> Chapter of Ezechiell. <hi>It ſhall come to paſſe, when Gog ſhall come: that my anger ſhall goe forth in my wrath, and I ſpeake the ſame in my iealouſie, and in the fire of anger.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26166:6"/>
               <p>Whereby it is cleare, that the Turke is nothing els, but the wrathfull anger of GOD, againſt our ſinnes, which he now, eſpecially, in his gracious viſitatirn, and reuelation of his holy word, in all places of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, findeth to be ſo great: that it may euen now be ſayd of vs, as it is written of <hi>Iſraell. The children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell ſinned againſt the Lord theyr God, which brought them out of the land of Egipt, &amp; ſetled themſelues againſt the Lord.</hi> And when the Lord ſayd vnto them, <hi>Turne away from your euill doings, and keepe my commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> They harkned not, but ſtifned their necks like the necks of their fore-fathers. Therfore are we threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo much the more: in ſo much as in theſe dayes, we haue more grace and warning through his holy Goſpel, then many of our fore-fathers, and predeceſſors.</p>
               <p>Whereby it followeth then. What can a man doe, or what will he doe, when he hath God himſelfe and the Turke, againſt him. But the chiefeſt and next way is, as he ſaith himſelfe: <hi>Turne away from your euill doings, and keepe my lawes and commaundements.</hi> For by that meanes we bring God againe to vs, and may with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort goe againſt our Enemies.</p>
               <p>And withall, let all Chriſtian people be here-with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, both high and low degrées, Super<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ours and Subiects, touching the great danger yet to come, of the profeſſed Enemy of Chriſtian name (the Turke) and what Enemies els ſoeuer there be: that euery one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe to God, kéepe himſelfe from falſe doctrine, and leane with all his endeuour, to the deere and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous word of God, and his holy Sacraments. To ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour himſelfe, as it were before God, to liue according to his word, and with good conſcience, both openly and ſecretly, to leaue of from euill, and to doe good. So then if euery one wil ſo doe: we may then be aſſured of Gods
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26166:6"/>promiſes, where he ſayth. <hi>Turne you to me, and I will turne me to you.</hi> The which he hath ſhewed by many notable examples amongſt his people, when they were ſoreſt oppreſſed of their Enemies, and in the very mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of their puniſhment, turned vnto God: God did alſo turne vnto them, and gaue them oftentimes great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and victory, againſt their Enemies.</p>
               <p>For ſo GOD ſayth furthermore himſelfe, that he wil puniſh the Enemies of Chriſtendome, <hi>Gog, Magog, Thuball,</hi> and
<hi>Meſech,</hi> that they ſhall fall vpon the hills of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> which is (as all Chriſtian Teachers doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it) in the lands of Chriſtendome, into which the ſame Enemies ſhall fall: and God will finally caſt the ſame Enemy, and all whatſoeuer is againſt his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, together, into the firy lake.</p>
               <p>Whereof we haue now (God be thanked) a faire ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, of the glorious victory, which we through Gods helpe, had at the ſtrong Towne of
<hi>Raab.</hi> Eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God heard the harty ſighing and earneſt prayers of his faithfull, himſelfe ſtanding by, and helping our Chriſtian Souldiers. If now the wicked (wherof alas there are alwayes more then godly) would turne away from their euill wayes, to the little heape of the godly, with true repentance, and with them call earneſtly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God: God would vndoubtedly ſhew vs yet greater helpe. And raiſe vp ſuch valiant Souldiers, and giue them ſuch harts and courage: that with the comfort of Gods helpe, dare goe vnder the very noſes of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Therfore let euery one, for the honour of God, helpe, and deliuery, for his owne temporall proſperity and ſaluation, be admoniſhed to repentance.</p>
               <p>For if the ſame haue not a right paſſage through vs: God can ſoone with-draw his helpe againe, that one land
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26166:7"/>after another muſt abide it, as <hi>Iſraell</hi> and <hi>Iuda</hi> and many Kings and kingdoms did, which héeretofore were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as hitherto is come to paſſe. And yet can God make a difference both of ſpirituall and worldly, with them which repent and amend: and them alſo which doe not repent.</p>
               <p>But becauſe prayer is the beſt armour, whereby we call vpon Chriſt in faith: let vs with harty thanks, for the obtained victory, calling euermore to God, with hart and mouth, ſay, <hi>We prayſe thee, O God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:26166:7"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
